<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Latency on Leonardo Benicio</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/tags/latency/</link><description>Recent content in Latency on Leonardo Benicio</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2025 10:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lbenicio.dev/tags/latency/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The 100‑Microsecond Rule: Why Tail Latency Eats Your Throughput (and How to Fight Back)</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/the-100microsecond-rule-why-tail-latency-eats-your-throughput-and-how-to-fight-back/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2025 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/the-100microsecond-rule-why-tail-latency-eats-your-throughput-and-how-to-fight-back/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;If you stare at a performance dashboard long enough, you’ll eventually see a ghost—an outlier that refuses to go away. It’s the P99 spike that surfaces at the worst time; the one you “fix” three times and then rediscover during a product launch or a perfectly normal Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s the hard truth: tail latency doesn’t just ruin your service levels; it compounds into lost throughput and broken guarantees. In systems with fan‑out, retries, and microservices, the slowest 1% isn’t “rare”—it’s the norm you ship to users most of the time. This is the 100‑microsecond rule in practice: small latencies multiply brutally at scale, and the invisible cost often starts below a single millisecond.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Scheduling: Trading Latency for Throughput (and Back Again)</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/scheduling-trading-latency-for-throughput-and-back-again/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/scheduling-trading-latency-for-throughput-and-back-again/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Schedulers encode policy: who runs next, on which core, and for how long. Those choices shuffle latency and throughput. Let’s make the trade‑offs explicit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="fifo-vs-priority-vs-fair"&gt;FIFO vs. priority vs. fair&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;FIFO: simple, minimal overhead; tail prone under bursty arrivals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Priority: protects critical work; risks starvation without aging.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fair (CFQ‑like): shares CPU evenly; may underutilize when work is imbalanced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="work-stealing"&gt;Work stealing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great for irregular parallel workloads. Each worker has a deque; thieves steal from the tail. Pros: high utilization; Cons: cache locality losses and noisy tails under high contention.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Latency-Aware Edge Inference Platforms: Engineering Consistent AI Experiences</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/latency-aware-edge-inference-platforms-engineering-consistent-ai-experiences/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/latency-aware-edge-inference-platforms-engineering-consistent-ai-experiences/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Large language models, recommender systems, and computer vision pipelines increasingly run where users are: on kiosks, factory floors, AR headsets, connected vehicles, and retail shelves. But pushing models to the edge without a latency-aware strategy is a recipe for jittery UX, missed detections, and compliance headaches. This guide dissects what it takes to build an edge inference platform that meets strict latency budgets—even when networks wobble, models evolve weekly, and hardware varies wildly.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>