<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Compliance on Leonardo Benicio</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/tags/compliance/</link><description>Recent content in Compliance on Leonardo Benicio</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 13:25:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lbenicio.dev/tags/compliance/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Auditing the Algorithm: Building a Responsible AI Pipeline That Scales</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/auditing-the-algorithm-building-a-responsible-ai-pipeline-that-scales/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 13:25:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/auditing-the-algorithm-building-a-responsible-ai-pipeline-that-scales/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When regulators asked for evidence that our AI systems behave responsibly, we realized spreadsheets and ad hoc reviews wouldn&amp;rsquo;t suffice. Our models influenced credit decisions, hiring suggestions, and medical triage. Stakeholders demanded more than accuracy—they wanted fairness, explainability, and accountability. We responded by building a responsible AI audit pipeline woven into development, deployment, and operations. This article shares how we did it: the processes, tooling, and cultural shifts that turned compliance into continuous curiosity.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Countdown to Quantum: Migrating an Enterprise to Post-Quantum Cryptography</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/countdown-to-quantum-migrating-an-enterprise-to-post-quantum-cryptography/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2024 16:40:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/countdown-to-quantum-migrating-an-enterprise-to-post-quantum-cryptography/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When the first credible quantum threat report reached our CISO&amp;rsquo;s desk, the reaction was cautious curiosity. Quantum computers capable of breaking RSA-2048 remain years away, but data harvested today could be decrypted decades later. We handle sensitive customer contracts, healthcare records, and government workloads. Waiting for the quantum threat to manifest felt irresponsible. So we embarked on a multi-year migration to post-quantum cryptography (PQC). This post documents the journey—strategy, tooling, experiments, and the human moments that kept the program afloat.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Instrumenting Without Spying: Privacy-Preserving Telemetry at Scale</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/instrumenting-without-spying-privacy-preserving-telemetry-at-scale/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 May 2021 18:45:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/instrumenting-without-spying-privacy-preserving-telemetry-at-scale/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Three years ago, our observability dashboards flickered ominously: ingestion lag, missing metrics, red error bars. We had paused telemetry from millions of devices after discovering that our pipeline collected more than we were comfortable storing. The pause kept our promise to users—but left engineers blind. We needed a way to reinstate observability without betraying trust. The result was a radical redesign: a privacy-preserving telemetry system that treats data minimization as a feature, not a compliance chore.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>