<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Databases on Leonardo Benicio</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/categories/databases/</link><description>Recent content in Databases on Leonardo Benicio</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lbenicio.dev/categories/databases/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Write-Ahead Logging: The Unsung Hero of Database Durability</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/write-ahead-logging-the-unsung-hero-of-database-durability/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/write-ahead-logging-the-unsung-hero-of-database-durability/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Every database makes a promise: your committed data will survive crashes, power failures, and hardware hiccups. This promise—durability—seems simple until you consider the physics. Disks are slow. Memory is volatile. Writes can be reordered. Yet somehow, databases deliver both durability and performance. The secret weapon? Write-ahead logging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="1-the-durability-problem"&gt;1. The Durability Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider what happens when you execute &lt;code&gt;UPDATE accounts SET balance = balance - 100 WHERE id = 42&lt;/code&gt;. The database must:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>B-Trees and LSM-Trees: The Foundations of Modern Storage Engines</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/b-trees-and-lsm-trees-the-foundations-of-modern-storage-engines/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/b-trees-and-lsm-trees-the-foundations-of-modern-storage-engines/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Every database faces the same fundamental challenge: how do you organize data on disk so that both reads and writes are fast? Two data structures have emerged as the dominant answers—B-Trees and LSM-Trees. Understanding their trade-offs is essential for anyone building or operating data-intensive systems. This post explores both in depth, from their internal mechanics to their real-world implementations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="1-the-storage-engine-problem"&gt;1. The Storage Engine Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before diving into specific data structures, let&amp;rsquo;s understand what we&amp;rsquo;re optimizing for.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>