<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Machine Learning on Leonardo Benicio</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/categories/machine-learning/</link><description>Recent content in Machine Learning on Leonardo Benicio</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lbenicio.dev/categories/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Inside Vector Databases: Building Retrieval-Augmented Systems that Scale</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/inside-vector-databases-building-retrieval-augmented-systems-that-scale/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/inside-vector-databases-building-retrieval-augmented-systems-that-scale/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Vector search used to be a research curiosity. Today it sits in the critical path of customer support bots, developer copilots, fraud monitors, and every product marketing team experimenting with &amp;ldquo;retrieval-augmented&amp;rdquo; workflows. The excitement is deserved, but so is the sober engineering required to keep these systems accurate and available. Building a production vector database is more than storing tensors and calling cosine similarity. It demands a full stack of ingestion, indexing, storage management, failure handling, evaluation, and a constant feedback loop with the language models that consume those results.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Latency-Aware Edge Inference Platforms: Engineering Consistent AI Experiences</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/latency-aware-edge-inference-platforms-engineering-consistent-ai-experiences/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/latency-aware-edge-inference-platforms-engineering-consistent-ai-experiences/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Large language models, recommender systems, and computer vision pipelines increasingly run where users are: on kiosks, factory floors, AR headsets, connected vehicles, and retail shelves. But pushing models to the edge without a latency-aware strategy is a recipe for jittery UX, missed detections, and compliance headaches. This guide dissects what it takes to build an edge inference platform that meets strict latency budgets—even when networks wobble, models evolve weekly, and hardware varies wildly.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>