<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Devops on Leonardo Benicio</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/tags/devops/</link><description>Recent content in Devops on Leonardo Benicio</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lbenicio.dev/tags/devops/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Adaptive Feature Flag Frameworks for Hyper-Growth SaaS</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/adaptive-feature-flag-frameworks-for-hyper-growth-saas/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/adaptive-feature-flag-frameworks-for-hyper-growth-saas/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hyper-growth SaaS companies live in perpetual motion. Every day brings new customer segments, compliance regimes, infrastructure bottlenecks, and competitive threats. Feature flags evolved from simple booleans to mission-critical systems that guard deployments, power experiments, share risk across teams, and surface real-time signals about user delight. Building an adaptive feature flag framework is no longer optional; it is the backbone of progressive delivery and organizational learning. This article offers a deep dive into the patterns, guardrails, and operating models needed to keep feature flags safe, observable, and aligned with business outcomes when your product is shipping at warp speed.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Sealing the Supply Chain: Zero-Trust Build Pipelines That Scale</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/sealing-the-supply-chain-zero-trust-build-pipelines-that-scale/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2023 21:10:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/sealing-the-supply-chain-zero-trust-build-pipelines-that-scale/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The day we discovered a compromised dependency in our build pipeline felt like waking up to find the locks on our headquarters replaced. The package arrived through a trusted mirror, signed with a familiar key, yet embedded a subtle time bomb. We escaped without production impact thanks to layered defenses, but the scare pushed us to redesign our build system around zero trust. This article chronicles that transformation—technical and human—from ad hoc pipelines to hermetic, verifiable, auditable delivery.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Latency-Aware Edge Inference Platforms: Engineering Consistent AI Experiences</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/latency-aware-edge-inference-platforms-engineering-consistent-ai-experiences/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/latency-aware-edge-inference-platforms-engineering-consistent-ai-experiences/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Large language models, recommender systems, and computer vision pipelines increasingly run where users are: on kiosks, factory floors, AR headsets, connected vehicles, and retail shelves. But pushing models to the edge without a latency-aware strategy is a recipe for jittery UX, missed detections, and compliance headaches. This guide dissects what it takes to build an edge inference platform that meets strict latency budgets—even when networks wobble, models evolve weekly, and hardware varies wildly.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Deterministic Monorepo CI Platforms: Engineering Consistency at Scale</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/deterministic-monorepo-ci-platforms-engineering-consistency-at-scale/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/deterministic-monorepo-ci-platforms-engineering-consistency-at-scale/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Monorepos promise unified visibility, atomic changes, and a single source of truth. They also create CI/CD nightmares if builds become flaky, nondeterministic, or painfully slow. Deterministic CI platforms tame that chaos by ensuring every pipeline run produces the same outputs given the same inputs—no matter which engineer kicks it off, which runner executes it, or when it happens. This article is a long-form walkthrough for platform teams charged with shipping deterministic CI in sprawling monorepos covering mobile apps, microservices, infrastructure code, and ML assets. Expect hard-earned lessons, architectural blueprints, and operational playbooks drawn from companies that run tens of thousands of jobs per day without losing their sanity.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>