<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Supply-Chain on Leonardo Benicio</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/tags/supply-chain/</link><description>Recent content in Supply-Chain on Leonardo Benicio</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2023 21:10:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lbenicio.dev/tags/supply-chain/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Sealing the Supply Chain: Zero-Trust Build Pipelines That Scale</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/sealing-the-supply-chain-zero-trust-build-pipelines-that-scale/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2023 21:10:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/sealing-the-supply-chain-zero-trust-build-pipelines-that-scale/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The day we discovered a compromised dependency in our build pipeline felt like waking up to find the locks on our headquarters replaced. The package arrived through a trusted mirror, signed with a familiar key, yet embedded a subtle time bomb. We escaped without production impact thanks to layered defenses, but the scare pushed us to redesign our build system around zero trust. This article chronicles that transformation—technical and human—from ad hoc pipelines to hermetic, verifiable, auditable delivery.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Software Supply Chain Security: SBOMs, Sigstore, Reproducible Builds, and Attestation</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/software-supply-chain-security-sboms-sigstore-reproducible-builds-and-attestation/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/software-supply-chain-security-sboms-sigstore-reproducible-builds-and-attestation/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The software supply chain is the set of processes, tools, and artifacts that transform source code into software that runs in production. Protecting that supply chain is critical: compromises at any step — compromised dependencies, corrupted CI/CD pipelines, or forged releases — can lead to large-scale incidents that affect thousands of downstream systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post explains the modern toolbox for defending the software supply chain: Software Bill of Materials (SBOM) formats and generation, provenance and attestation concepts, Sigstore for transparent signature &amp;amp; provenance, reproducible builds, SLSA (Supply chain Levels for Software Artifacts), secure signing and key management, package ecosystem-specific hazards (npm, PyPI, crates.io), and operational practices for CI/CD and incident response.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Deterministic Monorepo CI Platforms: Engineering Consistency at Scale</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/deterministic-monorepo-ci-platforms-engineering-consistency-at-scale/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/deterministic-monorepo-ci-platforms-engineering-consistency-at-scale/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Monorepos promise unified visibility, atomic changes, and a single source of truth. They also create CI/CD nightmares if builds become flaky, nondeterministic, or painfully slow. Deterministic CI platforms tame that chaos by ensuring every pipeline run produces the same outputs given the same inputs—no matter which engineer kicks it off, which runner executes it, or when it happens. This article is a long-form walkthrough for platform teams charged with shipping deterministic CI in sprawling monorepos covering mobile apps, microservices, infrastructure code, and ML assets. Expect hard-earned lessons, architectural blueprints, and operational playbooks drawn from companies that run tens of thousands of jobs per day without losing their sanity.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>