<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Networking on Leonardo Benicio</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/tags/networking/</link><description>Recent content in Networking on Leonardo Benicio</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lbenicio.dev/tags/networking/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>TCP Congestion Control: From Slow Start to BBR</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/tcp-congestion-control-from-slow-start-to-bbr/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/tcp-congestion-control-from-slow-start-to-bbr/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Every time you load a webpage, stream a video, or download a file, TCP congestion control algorithms work invisibly to maximize throughput while preventing network collapse. These algorithms represent decades of research into one of networking&amp;rsquo;s hardest problems: how do independent senders share a network fairly without overwhelming it? Let&amp;rsquo;s explore how TCP congestion control evolved from simple beginnings to sophisticated model-based approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="1-the-congestion-problem"&gt;1. The Congestion Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without congestion control, networks collapse under load.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Network Sockets and the TCP/IP Stack: How Data Travels Across Networks</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/network-sockets-and-the-tcp/ip-stack-how-data-travels-across-networks/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/network-sockets-and-the-tcp/ip-stack-how-data-travels-across-networks/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Every web request, database query, and API call travels through the network stack. The simple act of opening a connection hides layers of protocol machinery handling packet routing, reliable delivery, congestion control, and flow management. Understanding how sockets work and how data traverses the TCP/IP stack illuminates why networks behave as they do and how to build efficient networked applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="1-the-network-stack-overview"&gt;1. The Network Stack Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before diving into details, let&amp;rsquo;s see the complete picture.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>