<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Scheduling on Leonardo Benicio</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/tags/scheduling/</link><description>Recent content in Scheduling on Leonardo Benicio</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2025 10:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lbenicio.dev/tags/scheduling/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The 100‑Microsecond Rule: Why Tail Latency Eats Your Throughput (and How to Fight Back)</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/the-100microsecond-rule-why-tail-latency-eats-your-throughput-and-how-to-fight-back/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2025 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/the-100microsecond-rule-why-tail-latency-eats-your-throughput-and-how-to-fight-back/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;If you stare at a performance dashboard long enough, you’ll eventually see a ghost—an outlier that refuses to go away. It’s the P99 spike that surfaces at the worst time; the one you “fix” three times and then rediscover during a product launch or a perfectly normal Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s the hard truth: tail latency doesn’t just ruin your service levels; it compounds into lost throughput and broken guarantees. In systems with fan‑out, retries, and microservices, the slowest 1% isn’t “rare”—it’s the norm you ship to users most of the time. This is the 100‑microsecond rule in practice: small latencies multiply brutally at scale, and the invisible cost often starts below a single millisecond.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Scheduling: Trading Latency for Throughput (and Back Again)</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/scheduling-trading-latency-for-throughput-and-back-again/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/scheduling-trading-latency-for-throughput-and-back-again/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Schedulers encode policy: who runs next, on which core, and for how long. Those choices shuffle latency and throughput. Let’s make the trade‑offs explicit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="fifo-vs-priority-vs-fair"&gt;FIFO vs. priority vs. fair&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;FIFO: simple, minimal overhead; tail prone under bursty arrivals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Priority: protects critical work; risks starvation without aging.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fair (CFQ‑like): shares CPU evenly; may underutilize when work is imbalanced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="work-stealing"&gt;Work stealing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great for irregular parallel workloads. Each worker has a deque; thieves steal from the tail. Pros: high utilization; Cons: cache locality losses and noisy tails under high contention.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Process Scheduling and Context Switching: How Operating Systems Share the CPU</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/process-scheduling-and-context-switching-how-operating-systems-share-the-cpu/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/process-scheduling-and-context-switching-how-operating-systems-share-the-cpu/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A single CPU core can only execute one instruction stream at a time, yet modern systems run hundreds of processes simultaneously. This illusion of parallelism requires the operating system to rapidly switch between processes, giving each a slice of CPU time. The scheduler—the component that decides who runs next—profoundly affects system responsiveness, throughput, and fairness. Understanding scheduling reveals why your interactive applications feel smooth or sluggish and why some workloads perform better than others.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>When Data Centers Learned to Sleep: Energy-Aware Scheduling in Practice</title><link>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/when-data-centers-learned-to-sleep-energy-aware-scheduling-in-practice/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2019 09:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lbenicio.dev/blog/when-data-centers-learned-to-sleep-energy-aware-scheduling-in-practice/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The first time we let a data center &amp;ldquo;sleep&amp;rdquo; during daylight hours felt reckless. Customers trusted us with near-infinite elasticity. Flipping servers into deep power states to save energy sounded like penny-pinching, not engineering. Yet the math was undeniable: idling a hyperscale fleet burned as much electricity as a mid-size city. This post tells the story of how we evolved from skepticism to confidence, building energy-aware scheduling systems that keep promises while honoring planetary limits.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>